<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and citizens of London at Bow-Church on the 29th of May 1682.</title>
            <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5415</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12900895</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12900895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69701)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 840:26, 977:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and citizens of London at Bow-Church on the 29th of May 1682.</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York, and University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
                  <note>Written by Benjamin Calamy.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John V, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95241:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor, ALDERMEN, AND Citizens of London. At <hi>BOW-CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi> on the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BENJAMIN CALAMY,</hi> D. D. One of his Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95241:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95241:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable Sir <hi>JOHN MOORE,</hi> Lord Mayor OF LONDON, And to the COURT OF ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is nothing in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon, that could recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:95241:3"/>Acceptance, beſides its plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the honeſty of its deſign: nor could any other Conſideration have prevailed with me to expoſe it to the View and Cenſure of this pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Age, but only fear of ſeeming to contradict the Doctrine I taught, <hi>Of ſtrict Obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Right Honourable, Your moſt humble and Obedient Servant,</hi> BENJAMIN CALAMY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95241:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd <hi>May</hi> 29. 1682. </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ON S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> JOHN 5.14.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Afterwards Jeſus findeth him in the Temple, and ſaid unto him, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thou art made whole, ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHat this Perſon, to whom our Saviour gave this good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in my Text, was doing in the <hi>Temple,</hi> is not very hard to determine. It was ſurely the moſt proper place for him to be found in, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been lately bleſs'd with ſuch a miraculous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from an infirmity he had thirty eight Years laboured under, and after ſo long waiting, and many unſucceſsful attempts of getting into the Pool, e'en now deſpaired of ever being freed from it; till at the powerful command of the Son
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95241:4"/>of God, the impotent man received new ſtrength and vigour, took up his Bed, and haſtned to the Houſe of God, there to offer up, as may well be gueſs'd, his Sacrifice of praiſe for ſuch a ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing mercy.</p>
            <p>How much more becoming and Pious then is this our Solemn Anniverſary Appearance on this Day, in this place, to pay the Tribute of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouteſt Acknowledgments, and moſt hearty Thankſgivings for a deliverance, as great and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendous, as ever Gods mighty Hand and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched Arm hath wrought for any People, or Nation under the Heavens: Which, if we either conſider the Extremity we were reduced unto, or the greatneſs of the Miſeries we were redeemed from, or the Means by which ſo prodigious a Work was atchieved, or thoſe manifold and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Benefits that have ſince accrued to us from it, hath the Characters of the divine goodneſs and power ſo viſibly impreſs'd upon it, is ſo illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous an inſtance, ſuch an aſtoniſhing effect of Gods wiſe and gracious Providence over, and care of this Church and Kingdom, as no Age can paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, no Hiſtory can ſhew the like.</p>
            <p>Our Nation had long lain languiſhing under miſerable Oppreſſion and Tyranny, its blood and ſpirits exhauſted in an unnatural Civil War, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Execrable Murder of the late King and Martyr of ever Bleſſed Memory; in the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his preſent Majeſty and all the Royal Family; in the Subverſion of our ancient Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and inſlaving this Land to the wills and luſts of the baſeſt and meaneſt of the People: Our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95241:4"/>Church ſo famous for its Primitive Purity, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Government, wholſome Diſcipline, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Order laid in the Duſt; monſtrous Errors and Hereſies every where abounding, wild En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm and blind Zeal juſtling out all ſober Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: This was our ſad and piteous State, when after many defeats and vain endeavours of the Loyal Party to reſcue their Native Country from ſuch lawleſs Uſurpation sand horrible diſtractions; when we were at the loweſt ebb, juſt ready to fall into utter Confuſion; then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God appeared in the Mount, infatuating the Counſels, ſtrangely ſcattering the mighty and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Forces of our Enemies, and by a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful train of Providences, without War or Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to the amazement of the whole World, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored our moſt gracious Soveraign, the Light of our Eyes, the breath of our Noſtrils, to his Rights and Kingdoms, and placed him on the Imperial Throne of his Fathers; (may his Reign be Long and Proſperous) and with him our equal Laws and juſt Liberties, the glory of the Engliſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and which ought to be eſpecially mentioned in this place, the true reformed Religion with its ſupports and encouragements, our Church re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in its former Beauty and Authority, and all theſe ineſtimable Bleſſings with great Peace and Plenty continued to us, now theſe two and twenty Years. This ſurely was the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our Eyes. This is a day the Lord hath made and ought to be had in Everlaſting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
            <p>The divine Providence is indeed extended to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95241:5"/>the minuteſt things, takes care of Sparrows, and numbers the very hairs of our Heads; but yet it is more eſpecially and particularly engag'd in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and managing publick affairs, ſuch as are of great moment and benefit to Mankind, in the over-turning or raiſing up of Empires, in grand revolutions of State, in alterations of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the protection of the ſacred Perſons of Soveraign Princes, the chief Minſters of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, his Vicegerents and Subſtitutes here on Earth, on whoſe welfare whole Nations depend: And God Almighty ſeems on purpoſe ſo to have contriv'd and accompliſh'd the deliverance of this day, as that himſelf might have the ſole glory and praiſe of it. He would not admit any Rival or ſharer in the honour of this Renowned Work. It was effected neither by humane force nor wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. It had all along much of Miracle in it; the Nation contributing little elſe towards its own Salvation, beſides the united wiſhes and Prayers of all good men.</p>
            <p>I am ſure I ſpeak now the ſenſe we all had of this mercy, when it was firſt vouchſaf'd to us; and ſhall we ever forget the triumphant ſhouts and joyful Acclamations, with which his Majeſty was welcomed into this City, (ſhall I ſay?) or rather into the open Hearts and Breaſts of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? even thoſe that were obnoxious to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, yet rejoycing and conſiding in what they had heard of the goodneſs and clemency of his nature. Now after ſuch experience of his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mercifulneſs and God-like diſpoſition to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, (and perhaps never any one Man in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95241:5"/>World had opportunity of ſhewing greater) after ſo long continuance of thoſe manifold Bleſſings, which attended his glorious Reſtauration; let us not ſuffer our thankfulneſs in the leaſt to cool and abate, or thoſe impreſſions of Love and Loyalty, which the firſt ſight of his Royal Perſon (who was the deſire of three Kingdoms) had ſtamped upon us, to be in any meaſure worn out and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced.</p>
            <p>Indeed ſo regardleſs are ſome men of Gods Providence over this Nation, and ſo forgetful of his great mercies, that they do not care to come nigh any place or perſons that do devoutly and ſolemnly own them, All the Liberty and Peace, all the Wealth and excellent Religion which they enjoy, do not poſſeſs and affect them comparably to the Fears and Jealouſies of the loſs of them all. They are ſo willing and ſtudious to put out of their minds all former deliverances, that they talk, think of nothing but approaching Miſeries and Confuſions, and by this means go the likelieſt way to bring thoſe Calamities upon us. But though I thus ſpeak, yet there is great cauſe to think bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things of you here preſent, who are now Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to bleſs God, not only for reſtoring to us our Lawful Prince, but alſo for giving us ſuch a Gracious King to Reign over us.</p>
            <p>Wee have indeed a Country that is admirably fitted for Pleaſure, Profit and every thing that is deſireable: and we have a Prince, that anſwers to all the Gentleneſs, Mildneſs and Temper of our Climate. I know very well, people are much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to run backward to famous men, and great
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95241:6"/>Princes of Former Ages, highly extolling thoſe that have been long ſince dead and gone; when they have a mind to diſparage or undervalue thoſe that are our preſent Governours. But, if men would make a more juſt and impartial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, let them look now into the World, and ſee how other Nations are govern'd, and by whom; let them well conſider their Condition and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances abroad, and ours under our Prince, and try with themſelves, whether they would be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to remove into another Country for the ſake of a more eaſie and favourable Government; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other great advantages, both temporal and ſpiritual, we have ſo long enjoyed under the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign influences of his happy Reign, and will, we hope, be continued to us and our Children after us, unleſs by greater and new Provocations, or impenitent perſeverance in old, we run our ſelves into a worſe, and if it be poſſible, a more deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition, than we were this day delivered from.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>behold,</hi> by the miraculous deliverance of this day <hi>we are made whole:</hi> I beg your Patience, while I briefly apply the Exhortation in my Text to this ſolemn occaſion: <hi>Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee;</hi> where be pleaſed to obſerve theſe few plain things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Sin is generally the cauſe of temporal evils, which holds true eſpecially as to Nations and whole Societies, and Bodies Politick.</p>
            <p>God often afflicts particular perſons for their tryal, for the encreaſe and exerciſe of their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, to propound their example to the World,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95241:6"/>out of Love and Fatherly affection to them: and ſometimes notorious wicked men eſcape puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this State, becauſe the day of Judgment and recompence is to come hereafter; but it is otherwiſe as to Communities of men, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting of publick National Judgments. Here God exerciſeth a peculiar Providence over Kingdoms and Nations in this Life. He uſeth other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, than he doth in aſſigning the good or evil things of this World to private perſons. In his Providences to ſingle perſons he doth not always conſider their merit; but when a Land is laid waſte by a cruel War, when a potent State is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, when Rebellion is proſperous, when a flouriſhing People is given up to Slavery or Captivity, we may then truly ſay, Behold the deſtruction and deſolation that ſin hath made.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of which difference commonly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is this; that this Life is the only time of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, or rewarding ſuch Societies and Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Men. All ſuch civil relations to one another ceaſe in the other World. Every one ſhall then anſwer and account for himſelf only; and ſo in this life alone can Nations or Kingdoms, as ſuch, be either puniſhed or rewarded. We ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to give to God the glory of his Juſtice, and acknowledge that they were the ſins of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that gave ſucceſs and victory to our Enemies; which, notwithſtanding the undoubted goodneſs of the late Kings Cauſe, the undaunted Valour of his Friends, his own perſonal Innocence and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Vertue, yet betray'd him at laſt into
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95241:7"/>their mercileſs hands, which ſo long kept our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Soveraign from his rightful Poſſeſſions, and ſubjected the People to that very Arbitrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and Power of the Sword, the prevention of which was the ſpecious pretence of their firſt taking up Arms.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſully or eclipſe the Glory and Joy of this day by enquiring into the particular Sins, that brought the late Confuſions upon us, but only ſay thus much, That though his Majeſty hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly Pardoned them, as far as concerns his Courts of Juſtice, nay hath commanded us not ſo much as to mention them to the diſgrace, or damage of any perſons guilty therein; yet ſurely it is lawful, nay very expedient ſometimes to call them to mind, yea often to remember them, in order to the avoiding the like occaſions or practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the future, which once proved ſo fatal to us: That we ſhould never more give way to ſuch murmurings and diſcontents, ſuch fears and vain ſurmiſes, ſuch Diviſions and Factions, as then kindled thoſe Flames, which laid both Church and State in Aſhes, till their happy Reſurrection on this day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve further, that though publick Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Judgments be always thus inflicted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the meaſure and proportion of our ſins, yet the removal of theſe doth not always ſignifie that the Nation is reform'd, and made better, or that God is reconciled with us, and hath received us again into his favour. For the true cauſe may be only this, that God would now uſe other methods, would try other remedies; he alters his diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95241:7"/>and preſcription; finding the inefficacy of Judgments to awaken and amend us, that we hardned our ſelves the more under the ſtrokes of his Vengeance, he now deſigns to melt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve us with an amazing kindneſs. So that the Miſeries and Calamities of the late Times, and the Deliverance of this day, do both teach us the ſame Leſſon, preach the ſame Doctrine, <hi>That we ſhould ſin no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this manner God hath been pleaſed in this Age moſt ſigually to deal with this Kingdom, by an intermixture of Judgments and Mercies, that either by fair and gentle means, or by harſher and more ſevere uſage we may be prevail'd upon, and engaged to our duty.</p>
            <p>Pardon me if I ſay that God Almighty ſeems to have a great inclination to ſave this Nation, and make us happy, if ſo be we would but yield to be ſuch our ſelves. He hath not done ſo to other People; nay, what could he have done more to oblige and reclaim us, than what hath in the compaſs of a few Years been done? He hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited us with Rods, and with Scorpions, a long Civil War, a devouring Plague, and a Conſuming Fire, and the like: and hath not he ſhewed us greater mercies? that which we this day comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate, the preſervation of the Kings Life to this time, the late Diſcovery and prevention of the Popiſh Plot, the maintaining us hitherto in Peace and Tranquillity, notwithſtanding our preſent diſtractions and dangerous Convulſions. And therefore</p>
            <p n="3">3. If after all theſe various trials and means uſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95241:8"/>by God, we ſtill go on in our Sins, this mightily aggravates the guilt, heightens the provocation, and will certainly encreaſe our puniſhment. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. We now ſin after long and ſad experience of the evil and miſerable effects of it. When we have ſoundly ſmarted for our faults, preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſevere correction to commit the ſame, or the like again; this argues an incurable temper, or at leaſt calls for the ſharpeſt puniſhments to break ſuch obſtinacy and ſtubbornneſs. One would ſurely think there needed no other Argument amongſt us againſt Rebellion or Sedition in the State, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Schiſm or Diviſion in the Church, than the bare remembrance of what this Nation hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuffered by them; eſpecially this ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in this preſent Age, when the memory of it is freſh, and the Scars ſtill remain. Ye have felt pretty well to your coſt, what it is to want Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, what it is by Violence to oppoſe juſt Authority; Ye have your ſelves ſeen the horrid Conſequences of Republican Principles, unbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled Liberty, popular Reformation, and univerſal Toleration. Should we now ever fall into the ſame ſins again, nouriſh and foment the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and miſunderſtandings between the King and his People, take upon our ſelves in any caſe to reſiſt the Soveraign Power; we groſly offend againſt light and knowledge, and fair warning given us, and late experience already had of the evil of ſuch doings. This is to brave God, and to Challenge him to do his worſt, when men will dare again to venture on any of thoſe courſes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95241:8"/>which but lately were ſo miſchievous and deadly to theſe three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As thus to ſin after we have been ſo ſorely puniſhed for it, heightens the offence; ſo to ſin after ſuch mercies received includes the guilt of ingratitude, of all Vices the moſt heinous and provoking: and we do but very ill requite the Lord, nay we highly diſpleaſe him, if the ſenſe of his goodneſs this day manifeſted to us, doth not render us, as more obedient to himſelf, ſo alſo more dutiful to our Earthly Soveraign. For this glorious Reſtauration doth lay an Eternal Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon us all, of continuing true and faithful to the Government in all Points, and at all times; unleſs we will chuſe to provoke God by our mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous unthankfulneſs to find out new inſtruments of Vengeance, and make experiment of what yet greater ſeverities may avail for our amendment: <hi>Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome will be ready to ſay, What worſe thing can happen to us? Can we imagine a more wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Calamitous ſtate of Affairs, greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, Diſorders, and Dangers, than what we this day were delivered from?</p>
            <p>Though indeed it is not eaſily conceived what can be worſe than what hath already befallen this Nation, yet we muſt not think that God wants new methods of puniſhing and humbling us. His Vengeance is not yet quite exhauſted, He hath ſtill in reſerve the dregs of the Cup of his Wrath. One King was baſely Murdered, and yet through the mercy of God we have ſeen the lawful Heir Reſtored, and our ſelves redeemed from the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95241:9"/>of Ungodly and Unreaſonable Men; let us now have a great care that we do not bring the Nation into everlaſting Slavery, by provoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to take away this ſo well conſtituted Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment for ever from us. God may next time deprive us of our King, and never reſtore him again or if he doth, it may be without an Act of Oblivion. He may give us up as a Prey to a mighty Neighbour, or a Foreign Enemy. He may cut us off from being a People, as he once did that ungovernable Nation of the Jews, and make us an hiſſing and by word to all the Countries about us. He may take away the glorious Light of the Goſpel totally from us, and give it to a Nation that ſhall bring forth much better Fruit: Eſpecially as to you in this great City, who during the late Troubles in <hi>England,</hi> felt not near ſo much as what the poor Country ſuffered, it may now come to your Lot, for this place to be the Scene on which the next bloody Tragedy may be acted. And if God ſhould once more for oue ſins, (though we hope better things) ſuffer theſe preſent Heats and Animoſities and Contentions amongſt us to ferment and ripen into another bloody War, can we expect any other Iſſue, but that it ſhould end in the total deſtruction of ſuch an ungrateful Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration?</p>
            <p>To apply our Saviours words, St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.43. If <hi>the Devil</hi> of Faction and Sedition, which hath been for ſome time purged but of this Nation; ſhould againſt <hi>return into his houſe from whence he came, and when he is come, find it emply, ſwept and garniſhed,</hi> ready and prepared for its reception;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95241:9"/>
               <hi>He will then take unto him ſeven other ſpirit worſe than himſelf, and enter in and dwell there, and the latter end</hi> of that Nation <hi>ſhall be worſe then the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave the refore with that freedom and plainneſs, as becomes the place I now ſtand in, and the ſervice I am now called to, to recommend to you ſome few things, which the deliverance we this day commemorate doth more eſpecially ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us all unto, by which we may beſt contribute towards the continuance of thoſe great mereies we now bleſs God for; and prevent our falling into the ſame or greater miſchiefs than thoſe we not long ago laboured under.</p>
            <p>The firſt I ſhall mention is this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Quiet and peaceable ſubjection to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment on this Day reſtored and re-eſtabliſhed, and that for Conſcience ſake, out of fear of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending God.</p>
            <p>I know the very naming of this will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſome men, who cannot endure to hear this Doctrine out of the Pulpit. Such gravely bid us Preach <hi>Jeſas Chriſt and him Crucified,</hi> and not to meddle with ſtate Affairs, or matters of Government. By this teſt they tell you, you ſhall know thoſe amongſt us, that have a mind to be ſooneſt prefer'd, or who are Friends to Arbitrary Power, or ſtrive to pleaſe the Court, by Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſuch ſtrict Obedience to the King; that we <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> ought to be quiet and ſilent, and not concern our ſelves in any publick Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions. This is the common objection and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt <hi>Clergymen</hi> this day.</p>
            <p>But truly I think this very excuſable in them,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95241:10"/>if not highly commendable, were there no better reaſon for it than this; That by this frequent and earneſt perſwading people to exact ſubmiſſion and conſtant adherence to the preſent Government, they make ſome amends for that great miſchief that was done out of Pulpits in the late Times, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary talk and infinuations.</p>
            <p>But why, I pray, muſt we be the only men, whoſe Mouths muſt at ſuch a time as this be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped? Let thoſe, who are leaſt guilty in this kind, throw the firſt ſtone at us. For who is there amongſt theſe wiſe men, that are ſo apt to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed at Divines medling with matters of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but himſelf takes the free liberty on all occaſions to canvaſs and cenſure all matters of State, paſſing his ſhrew'd Judgment, and deſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on every thing that is done or ordered, though never ſo much above his Capacity; Correcting the Errors of the King and his Council, of which he is by no means a Competent Judge; having his head full of new projects and models of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Mountebank Receipts, and Infallible Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to Cure and ſettle the Nation, which he vents in all places and Companies with his notable remarks upon all Occurrences, though all this while he be a perſon never ſo meanly bred, or little vers'd in humane affairs. Indeed this is the <hi>Epidemical Diſeaſe of the times,</hi> and the Clergy ought not to be too ſeverely reprehended, <hi>if they have not wholly eſcaped the general Contagion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in truth, the ground of all this Charge and Accuſation is only this, That the preſent Clergy of <hi>England</hi> take all occaſions of ſhewing their own
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95241:10"/>Loyalty, and of encouraging the People to the like. They teach their Hearers to be obedient, and perſwade them to Peace and Submiſſion, and this they had need ſpeak often, and loudly too in ſuch turbulent and boiſterous times, as we now live in. This is their great fault and crime, and God grant that we may all live under this diſgrace, and dy under this Ignominy.</p>
            <p>And in doing this, we preach no other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but what our Saviour and Maſter did, than was taught by his Apoſtles, than was practiſed by the Primitive Chriſtians, and owned in all the Churches of Chriſt (never contradicted, but by the Papiſts, in order to the ſetting up of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Power of the Pope, and by ſome Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſince the Reformation, to make way for the pretended Kingdom of Chriſt here upon Earth;) but eſpecially maintained and defended in our Church of <hi>England; viz.</hi> That Soveraign Princes are accountable to God alone, That actual Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is due to them in all things, honeſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and, That in no Caſe by force or violence we may reſiſt them:</p>
            <p>Nay, we affirm further with equal truth, That we are bound to obey our Lawful Superiours, not only for fear of puniſhment, not only for conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, or out of any temporal reſpect; but alſo out of ſenſe of duty towards God, who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined it under pain of Damnation; who hath inveſted Soveraign Kings and Princes with ſome of his own divine Power and Authority.</p>
            <p>Nay, it is not ſufficient that we pay them all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Obedience, or outward Reſpect; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95241:11"/>Veneration and Honour is due to them (and that, though themſelves be vicious perſens, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched in their Lives, heretical in their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Tyrannical in their Government) yet we muſt pay them ſuch inward Reſpect and Reverence as is due to their high Calling, and that great Place, and Character, and Image they bear here on Earth.</p>
            <p>Nay further yet, we muſt not ſo much as ſpeak, or think meanly, ſlightly or rudely of them: <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought;</hi> much more we ought not upon any account to vilify or diſparage their Perſons or Government, nor miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent or carp at their Proceedings, when they ſuit not with our preſent humour or underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nor complain of, or ſaucily inveigh againſt their Adminiſtration; nor do or ſay any thing that tends to leſſen their Reputation, to weaken their Authority, or to bring them into contempt; by which means they become leſs able to ſerve thoſe great ends, for which Government was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted.</p>
            <p>We ought not eſpecially to lay all miſcarriages or misfortunes of the times at their Door. For though Kings and Princes be but men, and men of the ſame Paſſions and Infirmities with other Mortals; yet the inconveniences and troubles that at any time ariſe in a Kingdom, do not always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the unskilfulneſs or neglect of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, but in a great part from the perverſe and unmanageable temper of the People. In a word, It is not more our duty than our priviledge and happineſs to Obey. This is our grand Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95241:11"/>not to be troubled with the Cares, and yet to enjoy the bleſſed Fruits of Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing I would recommend to you is this, That every one of us ſhould firſt and chiefly mind his own private duty, that belongs to him in that ſtation Gods Providence hath placed him in here; and to be ſure to amend and reform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, before he goes about to reform others, or the publick. Peace and good order can never be preſerved long without this; that every one ſhould keep his own proper rank, and follow his own work and calling, and act his own part aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd him on this great Theatre of the World, well and to the Life; leaving publick affairs to thoſe who have authority and ability to manage them; things ſacred to thoſe who are lawfully called to adminiſter them; all private perſons keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within their own bounds, and doing their own buſineſs they are bred to and fitted for.</p>
            <p>It is in all Societies as in an Army; wherein, it every inferiour Officer diligently minds his own Charge, and every ſingle Souldier keeps his own Place; and ſtoutly maintains his Ground and Poſt, and the General over looks and governs the whole, every one being ready punctually to Execute, not diſpute his Commands; then is good order and diſcipline maintain'd, and ſuch a Body cannot be eaſily broken. But when every private Souldier ſhall neglect his own place and duty to direct his Captain; and every Captain thinks himſelf wiſe enough to Lead and Command the whole Army, and is adviſing his General, and leaves his own Company to inſtruct his fellow Captains, not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95241:12"/>with their Conduct; what can this breed, but ſudden tumult and confuſion, till they all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a cheap prey to their Enemies? the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is eaſy.</p>
            <p>It hath indeed never been well with us in this Nation, ſince this itch of hearing and telling pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick News hath ſo notoriouſly infected all ſorts of men amongſt us. In which alone too many in this City ſcandalouſly ſpend ſo great a part of their Life, to the irreparable loſs of their precious time, neglect of their Trades and Religious Duties, and oftentimes to the utter ruine of themſelves and Families; who whilſt they ſhould be in their Shops, following their ſecular Profeſſions, are buſy in mending of the State, and reforming of publick abuſes and grievances, which concern them not; and thus diſorder the ranks of men, and ruffle and pervert the due courſe of things, and as much as in them lies, Dethrone, Depoſe thoſe whom God hath ſet over us for that very end, to take care of the publick Peace and Safety.</p>
            <p>But alas, Gentlemen, you are too preſumptuous and conſident above your reach and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Let me tell you, this is impudence and ill manners, were there no other vice or miſchief in it, for every conceited Pedant as if he were inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Politicks, or pert Tradeſman, that can but make a ſhift to ſpell out a <hi>Gazetie,</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to wield Scepters and rule Kingdoms. You ought not in modeſty to pretend to Wit and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity enough to comprehend ſuch affairs. Matters of Policy, the Arts and Methods of Government, are things too ſacred, and venerable, and auguſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95241:12"/>to be prophan'd by every unhallow'd hand. They are like the myſteries of Religion, which are not to be proſtituted to the Examination, and Diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of every capricious Brain, and vulgar Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Theſe are out of the reach of <hi>thoſe that hold the Plow, or that drive Oxen, whoſe talk is of their Bullocks, who give their mind to make Furrows, and are diligent to give the Kine Fodder.</hi> Theſe are not to be tranſacted at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> nor determined over our Cups, or at our ordinary Entertainment. Not but that every good and honeſt man is, and ought to be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the preſervation of his Prince, Religion and Country; yet always within the limits of his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Station; and when the Winds blow hard, and the Storm is great and violent, no ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain way of Shipwracking the Veſſel, as when every Paſſenger leaves his private Gabbin, and will needs be Pilot.</p>
            <p>We all complain of bad times, and evil days, and ſo indeed they are, and ſuch they will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue notwithſtanding our complaints of them. But then we muſt know, that they are only evil men that make evil dayes; and happy would it be for us, if all thoſe who complain moſt loudly of theſe evil dayes, would take ſufficient care not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards the rendring them ſuch. And if inſtead of vain and affected complaints, which only beat the air, men would in the fear of the Lord take themſelves to task, ſearch out what is amiſs in themſelves, firſt ſweep their own Door, would ſpend their time and uſe their Eyes more at home, be more curious and critical in obſerving
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95241:13"/>themſelves than other men, and become more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere againſt their own faults than they are againſt the miſcarriages of others; the World would ſoon be much mended, and we ſhould ſuddenly have far better days. Thou haſt thy ſelf in the firſt place given thee in charge to look after. For that chiefly thou ſhalt be accountable, and not for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick misfortunes; it behoveth us then to take care, whilſt we are ſo buſily employed in reforming others, we our ſelves do not become Caſtaways.</p>
            <p>Thus private perſons in their ſeveral ſtations, inferiour Magiſtrates according to the Sphere of their Power and Authority, and no further, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending every one conſcientiouſly to his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per work and buſineſs, would go very far towards the maintaining of order and quiet, ſecuring the publick Peace, and making the Government both eaſy and proſperous.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In order to the preventing any evils we fear, or the obtaining or continuing of the greateſt good, we muſt not uſe any unlawful or indirect means. This is the moſt pernicious and damnable Doctrine of <hi>Rome,</hi> though not always publickly owned, yet greedily ſwallow'd amongſt them; and proved ſufficiently from their unwearied pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices; that in order to the propagation of their Faith or Church, any thing, every thing becomes lawful; Killing and Maſſacring no Murder, Lying and Perjury no ſin or injury. That ſo good and great an end will juſtify and ſanctify all actions. Nay, have not we had inſtances amongſt our ſelves in this Kingdom of the greateſt wickedneſs, and villanies committed by pretended Proteſtants, for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95241:13"/>Gods glory and for ſetting up the Goſpel and pure worſhip of Chriſt? and indeed well meaning men, but of great paſſions, are not a little apt to this. When they are ſecured of the goodneſs and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of their end, their minds are ſo intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and they are ſo hot and eager in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it, that they allow not themſelves leiſure and patience to conſider the lawfulneſs and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diency of the means they uſe for the compaſſing of it.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, we have not ſo learned Chriſt. We are not to do the leaſt evil, though the greateſt good may come by it. Our Religion teacheth us to ſuffer the greateſt evils, rather than forſake or renounce it; but not to do the leaſt evil, even for the maintenance of it; and it will be our great glory and commendation, nay I may add our intereſt and ſafety too, to hold true to this principle, neither to do, nor to conſent unto any unwarrantable action, though it be to keep out Popery and Slavery, no, not to ſave three Kingdoms. And thus doing and ſuffering we highly manifeſt our full truſt in God, and ſignally entitle our ſelves to his Protection.</p>
            <p>The ſtory of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> is remarkable to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>David with the choſen men of Iſrael</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing the Ark of the Lord, in a new Cart from the Houſe of <hi>Abinadab,</hi> as you may ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> drove the Cart. Now the Oxen chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſtumble, and the Ark was ſhaken, ſo that it ſeemed ready to fall. It was not lawful for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah,</hi> (though what the particular reaſon was, is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly diſputed by learned men) to touch the Ark.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95241:14"/>Yet out of great zeal and good meaning to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a thing ſo diſhonourable to God and their Religion, as the fall of the Ark to the ground would have been, he ſuddenly put forth his hand, and took hold of it, and he died in the place. God would not ſuffer ſo much as a ritual, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial law to be openly broken, though it were to ſave the Ark, the ſignal of his divine preſence amongſt them, from falling. God ſtood not in need of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi>'s help againſt his own Law and Command.</p>
            <p>The intereſt of Religion it ſelf is not to be kept up, or carried on by any courſes or practices that our Religion condemns. If we truſt God and the goodneſs of our cauſe, we muſt be ſure no means in the defence of it, but ſuch as God doth allow: or can we ſhew greater diffidence in God, than when we think to ſerve him by our iniquity and unrighteouſneſs, by our ſins to advance his glory, as if God were at a loſs in ſome circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to defend his tottering Church and People, unleſs we help'd him out a little in a time of great need, by ſtretching our Conſciences and venturing on ſomething that he hath forbid? People muſt not take care of God and his cauſe againſt Gods mind.</p>
            <p>Whenever therefore by projects of our own invention not approved of by God, we contrive to avoid perſecution, or preſerve the Proteſtant Religion, which yet we hope the neceſſity of the times, and exigency of the preſent State of Affairs will excuſe; when we endeavour after ſettlement and ſalvation by any irregular, indirect means, we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95241:14"/>put our ſelves out of Gods way and protection, renounce his care and providence over us; we declare that we are weary of waiting upon him, are afraid to depend on him, chuſe rather to ſtand upon our own Legs, or, as <hi>Saul</hi> did, when God had forſaken him, run to the <hi>Devil</hi> for help and advice. Nay, this is the moſt ready way to loſe, to betray our Religion, when we attempt to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it by unlawful means. God and his Church will ſtand, but when men do overact it, and are over-eager and buſy, they labour not ſo much at Gods cauſe as their own.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In order to the continuance of theſe great mercies to us, which we this day bleſs God for, I know nothing more effectual, than our Conſcientious and conſtant adhering to the Church, as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed; a Church reformed with the graveſt and matureſt deliberation, by the advice and with the conſent of the ſupreme power, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt and Primitive Ages; whoſe Doctrines are ſo Orthodox, its Liturgy ſo devout, its Government ſo Apoſtolical, its Conſtitutions ſo reaſonable and uſeful, its Ceremonies ſo few and decent, that no one can refuſe Communion with it, but upon ſuch principles, which if he holds to them, ſhall equally oblige him to refuſe Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with all the ſetled Churches, that are or have been in the Chriſtian World, excepting ſome few little Commonwealth Churches, but of very late Years firſt invented, and ſet up amongſt us. A Church moſt admirably fitted for the making of men ſubſtantially good and pious, juſt and loyal,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95241:15"/>peaceable and charitable, that incroacheth not upon the Right of Princes, nor impoſeth on the Faith of Chriſtians; that hath moſt remarkably run the fate of, and ſtood or fell with the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; which is the terrour of <hi>Rome</hi> and the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark of the Proteſtant Cauſe and Religion. And in all humane probability nothing can keep Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (of which we now ſtand in ſo much fear and danger, which is the great evil that now ſo ſorely threatens us) nothing, I ſay, can keep it out of <hi>England</hi> ſo much as being firm and true to this preſent eſtabliſhment, till our Governours ſhall ſee fit to make any alterations.</p>
            <p>And if ever that common Enemy again get en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance here, it muſt be through thoſe holes and breaches, which our needleſs Diviſions and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the Church have made.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of the old <hi>Britains,</hi> when the <hi>Romans</hi> firſt Conquered them, <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnant, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi vincuntur:</hi> Their divided ſingle Troops were preſently ſubdued by the united force of <hi>Caeſars</hi> diſciplin'd Legions. And the ſame way will the Romiſh Religion, if ever, gain admittance. It will ſoon ſurmount and cruſh all little ſeparated incoherent Congregations which might be reſiſted, and kept out by a well conſtituted united Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church.</p>
            <p>And therefore I cannot but ſay here, that none do ſerve Popery more ſucceſsfully, though, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, they know it not, nor deſign any ſuch thing themſelves, than thoſe, who are with both hands pulling down this preſent Church of <hi>England,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually pelting her with peeviſh exceptions, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95241:15"/>popular ſcruples, libelling her Biſhops and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and laying all the evils of the times to their Charge, ſlandering her Miniſters, vilifying her divine Offices, ſlighting her Cenſures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding her Inſtitutions. The faſter and ſurer this Church is eſtabliſhed, the more Intereſt, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Influence it hath, ſo much longer will Popiſh Idolatry be kept out of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all that ſome ill men are apt to declaim againſt our Church, as if it were Popiſhly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet Heaven and Hell, Light and Darkneſs are not more contrary one to the other, than the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Popery and the Religion profeſſed and taught in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And I pray God, he be not now by his late Providences teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Proteſtants the difference between Popery and Conformity, and ſhewing us that the little Finger of Papal Tyranny is heavier than the Loins of the Engliſh Epiſcopacy. If ever ſuch a ſad day happen in <hi>England,</hi> (which God in his infinite mercy prevent) that Popery ſhould be ſetled by a Law, men will then ſee, what little reaſon they had to cry down our preſent Church as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, or the Miniſters of it as Papiſts in <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade,</hi> or the publick Prayers as the ſame with the Maſs-Book, or our kneeling at the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as the ſame with the Adoration of the Hoſt. They will then gladly wiſh for theſe days again, that they might have but once more the opportunity of ſerving God in publick, though with all the Ceremonies our Church enjoins. What an Happineſs would they account that Liberty which now they are too apt to call Perſecution?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95241:16"/>thus the unreaſonable ſuſpicious and groundleſs clamours of ſome men againſt our Church, as draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too nigh, and approaching daily nearer to Popery, may ſoon bring or provoke God juſtly to inflict that great evil both upon themſelves and us.</p>
            <p>Now as there are two ways of ſecuring a Town beſieged by Enemies, weakning the force of the Enemy without us, and ſtrengthning and better fortifying our own Walls, and encreaſing the number of our Souldiers and Defendants: So are there two ways of keeping out Popery, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcountenancing, executing the penal Laws againſt all thoſe of the Romiſh Faction; but alſo by daily adding to the ſtrength of our own Church by healing her wounds, and making up her Breaches, by reſtoring due Authority to its Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Reverence to its Miniſters, by the coming in of thoſe who have diſſented from and deſerted her, and for our common ſafety at leaſt joining with us, ſacrificing all petty intereſts and bones of contention to the publick Peace; and then through Gods bleſſing, and the goodneſs of our Governours, we may be able to ſtand our ground, notwithſtanding the unwearied attempts and artifices of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt us.</p>
            <p>It is the great Policy of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that whatever differences ariſe amongſt them in matters of opinion, (and they are ſeveral, and thoſe managed with a great deal of heat and zeal, notwithſtanding their pretence to infalibillity) yet they all agree to adhere faſt unto, and by all means to promote Holy Church. Whereas our miſchief
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95241:16"/>and folly is, that every little difference conſtitutes a new Party, and we divide in intereſt; and ſo that we may but pull down thoſe that oppoſe us, we care not though we let in thoſe that will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Machiavel</hi> in his Diſcourſes upon <hi>Livy</hi> layes it down for an error in Politicks, by force to invade any City or Kingdom, when there are great Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Seditions amongſt the People; this being the moſt ready way to unite them all againſt the common danger. Let them but alone, ſaith he, or help a little to encreaſe and widen their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and they ſhall ruine and deſtroy themſelves without putting their Enemies to any trouble. And truly we may well account our Diſſenſions and Diviſions incurable, if our late and preſent fears and dangers be not ſufficient to put an end to them. When <hi>Hannibal</hi> is at the Gates, it is no time ſurely for men to be ſquabling and jangling againſt a Ceremony or a Form of Prayer.</p>
            <p>In this all Parties agree, all ſides teach and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, that there is no likely way of preſerving our common Religion, but by all Proteſtants uniting together, for the joint defence of thoſe things they agree in. And yet notwithſtanding all this good talk, are not our Religious feuds and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities greater, more fierce at this day than ever? Do not our Diviſions encreaſe? Do not our Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts run further from us, keep at a greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, inſtead of approaching as nigh as they could, or complying with us, as far as in their own Conſciences they judged lawful? Are not new terms of diſtinction, and opprobrious nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95241:17"/>Coined and paſs currant amongſt us? Is not Victory and Superiority ſought more than Peace and Unity? to give Laws and preſcribe to others, rather than amicably to agree, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or ſilence our difference? Theſe are things that forebode worſe to our State and Nation, than Comets or Prodigies. For the Civil Government it ſelf can never be quiet, or ſecure, as long as there are ſuch endleſs Diviſions and Separations amongſt us, and the Civil State will find it ſelf wounded through the ſides of the Church.</p>
            <p>As we would therefore preſerve the Peace of our Country, our excellent Religion, and rid the Nation of theſe fears of Popery, leſt a much worſe thing than what we have hitherto felt, come upon us, let us not only our ſelves continue true and faithful to this Church we were baptized into, and have the happineſs to be Members of; but alſo endeavour by all the ways of Prudence and Love, by all the Arts of Mildneſs and Gentleneſs, by all lawful compliances and condeſcenſions, to win over others into its Boſom and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In order to the engaging of God to the protection of our King, and Church, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the continuance of all thoſe mercies we now enjoy above any other People, let us all join our utmoſt endeavours to put a ſtop to that Floud of Atheiſm, Prophaneneſs and Irreligion, that hath ſo ſtrangely of late Years prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>Every Age, God knows, is wicked and ſinful enough, and the preſent doth always appear to be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95241:17"/>the worſt, becauſe <hi>we are better acquainted with the evil of that than of any other:</hi> yet ſurely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in any time, ſince Religion (ſhall I ſay?) or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility firſt entred into our Country, were men ſo impudent and barefac'd in ſinning, in pleading for it, in defending of it, as in theſe dayes in which our lot is fallen.</p>
            <p>Heretofore men were ſenſual and debauched, but then they did all they could to conceal their Vices, they ſinn'd with Modeſty, they would ſometimes bluſh for what they had done, and their Conſciences often miſgave them. But now men make a mock and ſport of ſin, they glory and boaſt of it, they have entertained wicked Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples agreeable to their practices; they not only neglect Religion, but reproach and deſpiſe it; not only forget God, but deny him; do all they can to baniſh him and his Providence out of the World; affront and blaſpheme him; burleſque his ſacred Writings, expoſing to ridicule and ſcorn all the moſt ſerious and holy things or perſons.</p>
            <p>This drolling, ſcoffing humour, which ſpares not God himſelf, his Providences, Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeems to be the peculiar reigning ſin of this Age; inſomuch that many are e'en afraid of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing ſtrict or Religious, leſt they ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to the buffoonry, and raillery of ſuch men, who think every thing wit, that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and prophane.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied, but that this open wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath encreaſed much upon us, ſince the Kings coming in; Atheiſm hath got ſtrange ground, and made many Proſelytes. And that there is an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95241:18"/>degeneracy and corruption both of Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Manners amongſt us, is the obſervation and complaint of all ſober perſons.</p>
            <p>The chief cauſe of which is not, as ſome would perſwade us, the Reſtauration of the King, and Church; but indeed the horrid Hypocriſy, and that great abuſe of Religion, which was ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the late times, is one of the greateſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the prophaneneſs and contempt of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in this; when ſo many made ſhew of the greateſt demureneſs and tenderneſs of Conſcience imaginable, and yet were not afraid to do the moſt ſhameful and diſhonourable things. This was apt to make men think, that Religion was nothing elſe, but a crafty care to abſtain from ſome ſins, to give our ſelves greater liberty in others, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them with leſs ſuſpicion. This hath given oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to many of looſe Lives, to look upon all Religious People as a pack of Hypocritical Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, only ſome to have better luck than others, in paſſing off the Stage undiſcovered.</p>
            <p>And yet all this while there is nothing in the World more unjuſt and unreaſonable than this. True Religion is not to anſwer for all that the Army-Saints did, who only profeſſed it to ſerve a turn, who took up the outward garb and dreſs of it, by it to deceive the ſimple and unwary, and palliate their leud deſigns; whoſe chief godlineſs lay in making of Faces, turning up their Eyes, in bold extemporary Effuſions, and canting in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtyle, and Proclaiming a Faſt before every Murder they committed. What ſuch men did, ought not in the leaſt to prejudice us againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95241:18"/>Piety, hearty and ſober Devotion, true Righteouſneſs, Peaceableneſs and quietneſs of Temper, and univerſal Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>But whatever is the true cauſe of this growth of Atheiſm, and Irreligion amongſt us, this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the publick Peace and Government is in no little danger from men of ſuch Principles and practices. For when all is done, Conſcience is the beſt tie of Allegiance, and they will always prove the beſt and quieteſt Subjects, who are moſt afraid of offending God. And they, who regard not the Soveraign Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, or his Laws, can never give ſufficient aſſurance of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to their Earthly Prince, or of Obedience to his Commands, any longer than it is their intereſt ſo to do. So that we cannot any better way ſerve the King, and the Government than by promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting amongſt all his People the fear of God, and a due ſenſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>So ſerviceable to the true intereſts of Kings, and the happineſs and peace of Societies, is true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that the Atheiſts have looked upon it and expoſed it as a ſubtile invention of ſome airy Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians to keep Subjects in awe and order. So that whether they be true or falſe, yet by their own Confeſſion the Principles of Religion are very uſeful to mankind; and if they are not true, yet it is great pity they are not; and Atheiſm ought to be proſecuted and puniſhed as deſtructive to publick Peace and order. They are abſolute Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Government that would free mens minds from the dread of inviſible Powers; and ought to be avoided as the peſts of human Society,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95241:19"/>who labour to bring Religion into contempt.</p>
            <p>And oh that I could now ſay ſomething, that might be of force to perſwade you all, to adorn the King's and Churches Cauſe, which you have ſo happily eſpouſed, by innocency of Life, ſobriety of Converſation, by a regular Devotion and unaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Piety, and unbounded Charity; that you would all take care to give unto <hi>God</hi> as well as to <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due.</p>
            <p>Let us but all in our ſeveral places live better than our Kings or Churches Enemies, and then let me tell you, we will neither fear their Swords, nor their Pens, their Weapons, nor their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is the prophaneneſs and debauchery, the Oaths and intemperance of too many amongſt us, that would pretend to be the greateſt Lovers of the Crown and Church, that do really moſt endanger both, that weaken our ſide, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and harden our Adverſaries. Let this be but your task to wipe off this ſtain, to anſwer this Objection, to remove this ſcandal from the Loyal Party; and I ſay it again, we need not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at what either Papiſts, or Fanaticks can ſay or do againſt us. Oh let not our heinous and crying ſins a ſecond time ruine and loſe ſo juſt and glorious a Cauſe, deſtroy ſo flouriſhing a Kingdom and Monarchy, overturn the pureſt and beſt conſtituted Church in the World. Let not our ſelves prove our own greateſt Enemies and Betrayers.</p>
            <p>It is not, believe me, wild huffing and hector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, extravagant Swearing and Drinking for the King and the Church; it is not our damning to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95241:19"/>the Pit of Hell either Papiſts or Fanaticks, that doth us any ſervice, or them any harm.</p>
            <p>We could e'en wiſh all ſuch men from amongſt us, but that we ſtill hope, at laſt they may be brought to a better mind. Though they add to our numbers, yet we loſe and ſink in our repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by reaſon of them, beſides that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God againſt us. We cannot wiſh worſe to the Kings Enemies, than that all ſuch, as hate to be reformed, would go over to their ſide, and credit their Party. We have already ſeen by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience, how far the mask and diſguiſe of Religion only prevailed and ſucceeded. What would the effect be, if ſo good a Cauſe were maintained and defended only by good men.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let us all add our conſtant and devout Prayers for the King, for the preſervation of his Life, the proſperity of his Affairs, and for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon his Government. In doing of this we only pray moſt effectually for our ſelves; this is a ſhort compendious way of wiſhing all good and happineſs to our ſelves and Country, earneſtly praying for the Kings Life. Theſe words, <hi>Let the King live,</hi> or <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> comprize in them all the outward publick bleſſings we can want, we can wiſh for. Then we pray for the maintenance of our Religion, the defence of our Church, the enjoyment of our juſt Rights and Liberties. We pray for the common welfare and ſafety, when we thus zealouſly recommend our moſt gracious King to Gods moſt eſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>This is a way, by which the meaneſt ſubject
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95241:20"/>may oblige his Prince, benefit his King; who may truly ſtand indebted for his Peace and Proſperity, in ſome meaſure, to the Prayers of his pooreſt Vaſſal. Thus though our Station be never ſo low and mean, our intereſt and influence ſmall and narrow, our Authority inconſiderable, yet we may prove great Benefactors to the publick, and do great good to three Kingdoms, by our faithful Interceſſions at the Throne of Grace for his moſt Excellent Majeſty,</p>
            <p>That God would preſerve his Royal Perſon from all outward Violence, or any inward Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; that he would continue his Strength and Health, would keep and guard him from all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, would Cloath all his Enemies with Shame, whilſt on his Head his Crown doth flouriſh; that he would inſpire him more and more with Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge, to Rule and Govern this great People; that he would direct and bleſs his Counſels, and proſper all that he takes in Hand; that after a long and happy Reign here, he may late, very late be tranſlated into the Immortal and Inviſible Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And as we pray to God on his behalf, ſo ought we moſt eſpecially this day, to praiſe God for him and thoſe manifold Bleſſings, which he hath been the happy Inſtrument under God, of tranſmitting down to us.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the Day wherein he was born, and the Night when it was ſaid, there is a Manchild conceived.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, that ſaved him from thoſe Bloody Hands, that ſo cruelly uſed his Bleſſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95241:20"/>Father, that covered his Head in the Day of Battel, that conveighed him ſafe through Crowds of his Enemies, when his precious Life was put to ſale; and after innumerable Dangers, by a miraculous Eſcape, landed him ſafe on a Foreign Shore.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, that preſerved him all along during a tedious Exile, that provided for him in the Wilderneſs, that kept him conſtant to that Religion and Church which his Royal Father died in, notwithſtanding great offers and temptations to change it.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, that upon this day brought him back again to his deſolate People, and hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto continued him a publick Bleſſing to this Nation.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, that hath given the King the Hearts and Affections of all his People.</p>
            <p>God be praiſed for his merciful Diſpoſition, for the unparallel'd ſweetneſs and benignity of his Temper, for the Mildneſs and Equity of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, his Love to the Church, his Conſtancy to the Proteſtant Intereſt, his Fatherly Care of his People.</p>
            <p>For all which, and all other Bleſſings, let there be aſcribed by us and all men, to God Almighty, the Father, the Son and Holy Ghoſt, all poſſible Praiſe, Thankſgiving, Adoration and Obedience, for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
